NYSUT Division of Research and Educational Services Files. 6174/003
Kheel Center for Labor-Management Documentation & Archives
- Educational Conference Board, 1959 (Box 16, Folder 15)
  Brochure, "A Vital Message for All Citizens of New York State interested in Children and the Future"; summary of the board's major fiscal proposals for 1959; booklet, "The School Budget and School Quality: 1959 Review of Fiscal Policy for Public Education in New York State"; booklet, "Are New York State Schools Good Enough? A Study Prepared by the New York State Educational Conference Board"; recommendations for legislative action
- Educational Conference Board – Staff Studies, 1958-1961 (Box 16, Folder 16)
  1959 Review of Fiscal Policy for Public Education in New York State Staff Study No. 1: "Cost of Living, Standard of Living, and Community Characteristics Related to the Purchasing Power of the Educational Dollar"; No. 2: "Public Tests of School Quality"; No. 3: "Government Costs and Tax Revenues"; No. 4: "The Involvement of Staff and Public in the Development of Policy and Budget"; No. 5: "Trends in School Expenditures and Tax Rates and the Stability of State Aid"; 1964 staff studies 1 & 2: "Public School Expenditures and Revenues" and "Resources and Taxation in New York"; "Staff Studies on Constitutional Provisions for Public Education in New York State," February 1958
- Educational Conference Board, 1958 (Box 16, Folder 17)
  Minutes; letter from Nelson Rockefeller asserting belief in strong state government responsibility for education, need for expansion of student financial aid; college education for every qualified student seeking it; report, "Toward More Quality Education: 1958 Review of Fiscal Policy for Public Education in New York State"; "Staff Studies on Constitutional Provisions for Public Education in New York State," February 1958
- Educational Conference Board Report, 1957 (Box 16, Folder 18)
  Report, "1957 Review of Fiscal Policy for Public Education in New York State: State and Local Support of the Foundation Program"; papers, "The Constitution and the Public Schools" and "Educational Growth and the New York State Constitution"; subcommittee report of the Tax Relief Committee of the Nassau Suffolk School Boards; minutes; correspondence
- Educational Conference Board, 1956 (Box 16, Folder 19)
  Reports, "Quality in Public Education and the Local Unit of School Government: A Review of Public Policy Relative to School Districts" and "1955 Review of Fiscal Policy for Public Education in New York State – Part II: The State Aid Program and Evolving Educational Needs"; press release, "Evaluation of Heald Commission Report," re state financing formula; summary of Heald Commission proposals
- Educational Conference Board, 1955 (Box 17, Folder 1)
  Minutes; articles of agreement; reports
- Educational Conference Board, 1954 (Box 17, Folder 2)
  Reports: "What Do Good Schools Do for Children?" and "The Price of Good Schools"; minutes
- Educational Conference Board, 1950-1952 (Box 17, Folder 3)
  Minutes; "Analysis of Public School Expenditure Trends in New York State"; other reports re funding; memos re importance of education
- Educational Conference Board – Long Island
- Long Island Educational Conference Board Meeting, 1980 (Box 17, Folder 4)
  September 9, 1980. Draft report by Long Island Educational Conference Board, An Analysis of "Study of Cost Reduction Opportunities for the Action Committee of Long Island, Inc.," done by Cresap, McCormick and Paget, management consultants, in the Sayville Union Free School District and Syosset Central School District, fall 1980, and cover letter from Santelli; minutes, "Review and Report," re meeting of review panel to discuss report
- Long Island Educational Conference Board – Syosset Report, 1979 (Box 17, Folder 5)
  Report by Cresap, McCormack and Paget re cost reduction opportunities in the Syosset school district, November 20, 1979
- Long Island Educational Conference Board (folder 1), 1980-1983 (Box 17, Folder 6)
  Report, "A Review of Two School District Management Studies," prepared for the Long Island Educational Conference Board, fall 1980; SUNY Albany report, "A Study of the Use of an Expanded Tax Base Approach to School Finance in the Mohawk Region: A Final Report Prepared for the Herkimer BOCES," November 1, 1982; proposal for a regional finance study for Suffolk County school districts to be conducted by the Long Island Regional Planning Board, March 10, 1982; related correspondence
- Long Island Educational Conference Board (folder 2), 1979-1980 (Box 17, Folder 7)
  Report by management consultants to the Syosett Central School District, "Study of Cost Reduction Opportunities for the Action Committee for Long Island, Inc," November 20, 1979; letter from Long Island Educational Conference Board re impact study to evaluate consultant recommendations, May 27, 1980; materials evaluating recommendations; newspaper clippings
- Long Island Educational Conference Board (folder 1), 1980 (Box 17, Folder 8)
  Report, "A Review of Two School District Management Studies," prepared for the Long Island Educational Conference Board, fall 1980
- Long Island Educational Conference Board (folder 2), 1980 (Box 17, Folder 9)
  As above, with handwritten notes
- Long Island Educational Conference Board (folder 3), 1980 (Box 17, Folder 10)
- Educational Conferences See: Conferences See: Regional Educational Conferences
- Educational Conferences, 1983 (Box 17, Folder 11)
  Memo from NYSUT Vice President Antonia Cortese asking for cooperation in limiting cost of conferences; letters to potential keynote speakers; camera-ready logos and halftones advertising conference; poster; miscellaneous materials
- Plattsburgh Institute, 1981 (Box 17, Folder 12)
  Flyer for 1982 NYSUT Annual Teacher Institute at State University at Plattsburgh; letter from Santelli to NYSUT vice president Toni Cortese noting dwindling numbers in attendance and even fewer first-time participants, suggestions for improvements, September 23, 1981
- Plattsburgh Institute, 1979 (Box 17, Folder 13)
  July 16-27, 1979. Agenda; letter from Plattsburgh professor of education to NYSUT Vice President Cortese re future of institute, urging return to two-week program, August 18, 1978
- Plattsburgh IV, 1977 (Box 17, Folder 14)
  July 25 - August 5, 1977. Agenda and related materials; correspondence
- Plattsburgh Workshop, 1975 (Box 17, Folder 15)
  Agenda
- Conference Needs Assessments, 1983-1985 (Box 17, Folder 16)
  Surveys of topics of interest for conferences
- Capitol District Regional Educational Conference, 1983 (Box 17, Folder 17)
  October 14, 1983. Agenda and related materials
- Oneida Upper Mohawk Educational Conference, 1983 (Box 17, Folder 18)
  November 5, 1983. Routine correspondence
- Central NY Educational Conference, 1984 (Box 17, Folder 19)
  April 6, 1984. Program; correspondence; photos removed
- Long Island Educational Conference, 1984 (Box 17, Folder 20)
  March 24, 1984.
- Lower Hudson Educational Conference, 1984 (Box 17, Folder 21)
  March 9, 1984. Financial report
- Mid Hudson Educational Conference, 1983 (Box 17, Folder 22)
  November 5, 1983. Survey results
- Plattsburgh Educational Conference, 1983 (Box 17, Folder 23)
  October 14, 1983. Financial report; routine correspondence
- Potsdam Educational Conference, 1984 (Box 17, Folder 24)
  May 2, 1984. Workshop descriptions; financial report; routine correspondence
- Rochester Educational Conference, 1984 (Box 17, Folder 25)
  April 6, 1984. Program; financial report; routine correspondence
- Southern Tier Educational Conference, 1983 (Box 17, Folder 26)
  November 5, 1983. Program; routine correspondence
- Tri-County Educational Conference, 1983 (Box 17, Folder 27)
  October 20, 1983. Program; routine correspondence
- Watertown Educational Conference, 1984 (Box 17, Folder 28)
  May 3, 1984. Program; financial materials; routine correspondence
- Western NY Educational Conference, 1984 (Box 17, Folder 29)
  March 31, 1984. Program; routine correspondence
- Capitol District Educational Conference, 1983 (Box 18, Folder 1)
  March 21, 1983. Program, noting Matilda Cuomo as keynote speaker on "What's Right with Education"; routine correspondence
- Central NY Educational Conference, 1985 (Box 18, Folder 2)
  March 15, 1985. Program; financial materials; routine correspondence
- Long Island Educational Conference, 1985 (Box 18, Folder 3)
  March 25, 1985. Program; routine correspondence
- Lower Hudson Educational Conference, 1985 (Box 18, Folder 4)
  March 15, 1985. Program, noting keynote speaker TV personality Steve Allen; financial materials; routine correspondence
- Mid Hudson Educational Conference, 1985 (Box 18, Folder 5)
  May 9, 1985. Routine materials
- Oneida Upper Mohawk Educational Conference, 1984 (Box 18, Folder 6)
  November 12, 1984. Evaluation forms
- Plattsburgh Educational Conference, 1984 (Box 18, Folder 7)
  October 12, 1984. Press release announcing workshop re merit pay
- Southern Tier East Educational Conference, 1985 (Box 18, Folder 8)
  April 18, 1985. Financial materials; routine correspondence
- Southern Tier West Educational Conference, 1985 (Box 18, Folder 9)
  March 17, 1985. Program; evaluation forms; routine correspondence
- Potsdam Educational Conference, 1984 (Box 18, Folder 10)
  October 11, 1984. Agenda; financial records; routine correspondence
- Tri-County Educational Conference, 1985 (Box 18, Folder 11)
  May 11, 1985. Press release re program; related correspondence
- Watertown Educational Conference, 1985 (Box 18, Folder 12)
  May 9, 1985. Agenda; related materials
- Western NY Educational Conference, 1984 (Box 18, Folder 13)
  October 22, 1984. Memos re attendance by Al Shanker; planning meeting announcement
- UFT, 1987 (Box 18, Folder 14)
  Program; agenda, routine correspondence
- Capitol District, 1986 (Box 18, Folder 15)
  April 3, 1986. Budget summary; press release announcing Alex Haley (author of Roots) as keynote speaker
- Central NY, 1986 (Box 18, Folder 16)
  April 4, 1986. Program re keynote speaker author Alex Haley; budget summary; correspondence
- Long Island, 1986 (Box 18, Folder 17)
  March 14, 1986. Program, featuring panel discussion, "Censorship in the Schools"; list of participating school associations, committee members; handwritten notes
- Lower Hudson, 1986 (Box 18, Folder 18)
  March 21, 1986. Budget summary; correspondence; program
- Mid-Hudson, 1986 (Box 18, Folder 19)
  March 13, 1986. Poster re keynote speaker, Al Shanker; related materials
- Oneida Upper Mohawk, 1985 (Box 18, Folder 20)
  November 1, 1985. Agenda; poster; invitations; evaluation forms
- Financial Data 1977 (Box 18, Folder 21)
  Financial data by district re stress and time management workshops
- Plattsburgh, 1986 (Box 18, Folder 22)
  May 7, 1986. Poster re stress management; related materials
- Plattsburgh, 1986 (Box 18, Folder 23)
  September 25, 1986. Correspondence with consultants re stress management talk
- Potsdam, 1986 (Box 18, Folder 24)
  May 8, 1986. Poster, invitation re stress and teacher empowerment talk, financial materials
- Rochester, 1985 (Box 18, Folder 25)
  November 15, 1985. Invitation, poster, biographical materials re speaker; related correspondence
- Southern Tier East, 1986 (Box 18, Folder 26)
  May 29, 1986. Poster re teacher empowerment; financial records
- Southern Tier West, 1986 (Box 18, Folder 27)
  May 6, 1986. Program; poster re humor; financial records
- Tri-County, 1986 (Box 18, Folder 28)
  April 24, 1986. Poster re demographic imperatives; related materials
- Watertown, 1986 (Box 18, Folder 29)
  May 28, 1986. Poster re keynote speaker Al Shanker; related materials
- Western NY, 1985 (Box 18, Folder 30)
  November 8, 1985. Steering committee minutes, September 19, 1985; program; related materials
- Western NY Mini-Retirement Conference, 1986 (Box 18, Folder 31)
  April 26, 1986. Steering committee minutes, February 27, 1986; program
- UFT Spring Conference, 1986 (Box 18, Folder 32)
  Flyers; program, "Prescription for the '80s: The Survival of Public Education," May 1981; correspondence re cancellation of 1982-83 conferences; re 1986 conference
- Teacher-to-Teacher Chairperson Meeting, 1981 (Box 18, Folder 33)
  June 6, 1981. Agenda; list of chairs and regional representation; memo to Vice President Toni Cortese expressing concern over adequacy of program budget, June 5, 1981; post-conference financial report
- Teacher-to-Teacher Wrap-up, 1982 (Box 18, Folder 34)
  May 26, 1982. Financial reports; correspondence
- Year End Summary Meeting, 1983 (Box 18, Folder 35)
  May 24, 1983. Agenda; invitation; correspondence
- Chairpersons Meeting, 1984 (Box 18, Folder 36)
  May 30, 1984. Agenda; list of conferences; thumbnail reports of chairs from regional meetings; suggestions for next year; list of responsibilities of chairs; proposed budget for 1984-85 educational conferences; financial report; correspondence; flyers
- Chairpersons Meeting, 1985 (Box 19, Folder 1)
  June 4, 1985. Financial reports; graphs showing change in attendance 1980-1985; list of chairs and regional representation; guidelines on vendor access to NYSUT activities
- Educational Issues See also: Task Force on Educational Policy See also: NYS Education Policy Seminar (Box 19, Folder 2)
  Papers prepared by NYSUT Division of Research and Educational Services on class size, teacher evaluation, auxiliary personnel in the classroom, alternative salary structures, alternative schools, instructional innovation and experimentation, school volunteer programs, accountability in education; related materials and correspondence.
- Staff Training on Educational Issues November 12-13, 1980 (Box 19, Folder 3)
  Memos re topics for 11/12-13/80 meeting; outline of issues for Local Presidents' Meeting, Elmsford, January 15, 1980; outline of issues for E.D.s 17 & 18 meeting, March 7, 1978
- Staff Training Evaluation Forms, 1980-1981 (Box 19, Folder 4)
  Filled-out forms re research department training; correspondence
- Educational Research and Dissemination (ER+D) Program, 1989-1991 (Box 19, Folder 5)
  Description of program, June 21, 1989; printed brochures; related correspondence
- ER+D (Educational Research and Dissemination) Program, 1996 (Box 19, Folder 6)
  American Federation of Teachers Educational Research and Dissemination Summer Institute announcements; related correspondence
- (AFT) Educational Research and Dissemination (ER+D) Program Convention, 1983-1986 (Box 19, Folder 7)
  Correspondence re inservice program; issues papers; AFT proposal to American Can Company Foundation for teacher recruitment incentive/internship project, October 1985; article reprints; training session agenda, 1983; newsletter updates
- AFT Educational Research and Dissemination Project, 1983 (Box 19, Folder 8)
  Executive summary re AFT program for National Institute of Education grant; correspondence; evaluation forms
- AFT Educational Research and Dissemination Project – Expense Vouchers, 1983 (Box 19, Folder 9)
  Facilitative correspondence
- AFT ER+D Coordination Meeting 1983-1984 (Box 19, Folder 10)
  Agenda for December 7-9, 1984, meeting; letter summarizing meeting, October 19, 1983, memo to NYSUT officials discussing program, March 3, 1983; related correspondence; handwritten notes
- AFT ER+D (Educational Research and Dissemination) Project, 1983-1986 (Box 19, Folder 11)
  Materials on classroom management; memos re project expansion; handwritten notes
- AFT Educational Research and Dissemination Training – Skidmore, 1984 (Box 19, Folder 12)
  Evaluation forms; facilitative correspondence
- ER+D – Skidmore, 1985 (Box 19, Folder 13)
  Training materials; handwritten notes
- AFT Educational Research and Dissemination Project, 1984 (Box 19, Folder 14)
  July 14, 1984. Correspondence, expense vouchers
- AFT ER+D Correspondence, 1984-1985 (Box 19, Folder 15)
  Newsletter updates on program; memos from school districts across the U.S.; article reprints on effective teaching; related materials
- ER+D, 1985 (Box 19, Folder 16)
  December 13-15, 1985. Agenda; article reprints and other teaching materials; site coordinators' reports; handwritten notes
- ER+D Meeting Americana, 1984 (Box 19, Folder 17)
  September 28-29, 1984. Discussion outline for meeting; NYSUT publication, "Some Helpful Information for Teachers," including guidelines on maintaining discipline by the NYC Board of Education
- ER+D Summer Preparation, 1985 (Box 19, Folder 18)
  Letters inviting local presidents to attend training
- ER+D Training, 1985 (Box 19, Folder 19)
  NYSUT Local Leaders' Guide 1985-86; memo re potential new sites for program, June 17, 1985; packet of article reprints on teaching techniques; list of sites
- ER+D Local Site Coordinators Meeting, 1985 (Box 20, Folder 1)
  March 29-30, 1985. Agenda; NYSUT Local Leaders' Guide 1983-84; handwritten notes; article reprint on effective classroom control
- ER+D Local Site Coordinators, 1985 (Box 20, Folder 2)
  Materials on teaching methods; local site coordinators' progress reports
- ER+D, 1986 (Box 20, Folder 3)
  "Publicity," packet of clippings and article reprints collected by AFT Educational Issue Department re ER+D program; list of local sites and coordinators as of June 30, 1986
- ER+D Invite Letter, 1986 (Box 20, Folder 4)
  Form letters sent to locals throughout the state, describing training program; comments on training by past participants
- ER+D Interest, 1986 (Box 20, Folder 5)
  Form letters responding to expressions of interest in training from locals; list of sites
- ER+D Training Session, 1986 (Box 20, Folder 6)
  July, 1986. Post-session form letters to local presidents and facilitative correspondence; publicity packets (article reprints and clippings)
- (AFT) Educational Research and Dissemination Program (ER+D), 1986 (Box 20, Folder 7)
  Fact sheet describing program as a professional improvement project; based on a research and observational framework; memos from Harry Lampman, NYSUT associate in research and educational services, re program updates, training logistics; list of locals involved in project
- ER+D (Educational Research and Dissemination), 1986 (Box 20, Folder 8)
  NYSUT Information Bulleting discussing NYS Mentor-Teacher Internship Program; proposed revisions to Commissioner's Regulations re mentor-teacher internship programs; site reports; correspondence
- ER+D Supply Materials, 1986 (Box 20, Folder 9)
  July, 1986. Handwritten evaluations re "strengths" of the week's workshop
- ER+D Program Coord. M+G, 1986 (Box 20, Folder 10)
  September 27-28, 1986. Meeting agenda; list of participants
- AFT ER+D Albany, 1986 (Box 20, Folder 11)
  May 31 - June 1, 1986. Meeting agendas; list of program sites; memos; paper presented at the annual meeting of the American Educational Research Association, "Bridging the Gap: The AFT Educational Research and Dissemination Program," April 1983
- ER+D, 1985 (Box 20, Folder 12)
  NYSUT booklet, "Some Helpful Information for Teachers," (no date)., c. 1976; memo from Lampman re upcoming meeting, with discussion outline; handwritten notes
- ER+D Meeting, 1987 (Box 20, Folder 13)
  September 18-19, 1987. Summary of meeting from Harry Lampman, September 29, 1987; related memos
- ER+D, 1985-1986 (Box 20, Folder 14)
  AFT description of Visiting Practitioner Program, A Teacher-University Collaboration Project, February 1985; report, "Experiences of a Visiting Practitioner at Stanford University," by Rudi Faltus, San Francisco teacher; Teacher Researcher Linker Study interview protocol, by Far West laboratory for Educational Research and Development, May 1985
- ER+D, 1986-1987 (Box 20, Folder 15)
  Memo from regional coordinators, forwarded to director of research and educational services Charles Santelli, noting concerns about the intensive nature of ER&D training July 19, 1986; memo from vice president Antonia Cortese to NYSUT Executive Committee recommending increase in ER&D budget for 1985-86; memos re program updates; article reprints on multiculturalism and mainstreaming
- ER+D General, 1987 (Box 20, Folder 16)
  Comments from participants on ER& training; handwritten notes; list of participating sites; letter of complaint about slowness of travel reimbursement, with reply from Harry Lampman, December 22, 1987; summary of meeting of program coordinators, September 18-19; summary of meeting of January 30-31; routine correspondence
- ER+D Harry Lampman, 1983-1985 (Box 20, Folder 17)
  Assessment of service needs of NYSUT locals, 1984-85; meeting agenda; routine correspondence; annual report, 1983-84; article reprints from American Educator; booklet, The Effective Principal: Achieving Equity and Excellence in Schools, U.S. Department of Education, disseminated by Mid-Atlantic Center for Race Equity, School of Education, American University, June 1983
- ER+D Meeting, 1987 (Box 20, Folder 18)
  January 30-31, 1987. Summary of meeting; related routine correspondence
- ER+D Meeting, 1987 (Box 20, Folder 19)
  January, 1987. Site reports; research topic status report; agenda for November 22, 1986, meeting; instructional materials, article reprints
- ER+D, 1987 (Box 20, Folder 20)
  March 27-29, 1987. List of attendees; expense vouchers, facilitative (routine) correspondence
- ER+D Invitations, 1987 (Box 21, Folder 1)
  Letters to teachers associations around the state inviting participation, including description of program
- ER+D General Dissemination Summary, 1986 (Box 21, Folder 2)
  Suggested topics for seminar materials, with comments by participants (?); lesson plans for National Science Week
- ER+D, 1987 (Box 21, Folder 3)
  Agendas; outline of initial expectations for local site coordinators; paper, "What Staff Developers Need to Know about Adult Learners," by Nancy Gadbow and Marcia Nabut; article reprints; seminar materials
- ER+D, 1987 (Box 21, Folder 4)
  August 9-16, 1987. List of participating sites; agenda; correspondence, incl. form letters for teachers who have completed training
- Educational Research and Dissemination Program (ER+D) Training and Resource Manual, 1983 (Box 21, Folder 5)
  Manual master pages for duplicating
- ER+D Locals Expressing Interest (Box 21, Folder 6)
  Correspondence; list of sites; directory
- ER+D Potential Sites, 1985-1988 (Box 21, Folder 7)
- ER+D Directory, 1991-1992 (Box 21, Folder 8)
  Directory of local site coordinators; correspondence re revisions
- ER+D – South Colonie, 1990 (Box 21, Folder 9)
  Action plan; correspondence
- ER+D – Troy, 1989 (Box 21, Folder 10)
  Coordinator's report; handwritten paper
- ER+D – Watervliet, 1989 (Box 21, Folder 11)
- ER+D – UFT (NYC), 1986-1989 (Box 21, Folder 12)
  Correspondence re training sessions in NYC; site report; diagram of NYC Teacher Centers Consortium training schedule
- ER+D – Shenendehowa (Capital District), 1987-1989 (Box 21, Folder 13)
- ER+D – Schenectady, 1986-1987 (Box 21, Folder 14)
- ER+D – Rochester, 1986-1988 (Box 21, Folder 15)
  Rochester Teacher Center Partial Listing of Semester II Workshops; correspondence; site report; handwritten paper
- ER+D – Greenwich (Capital District), 1988-1989 (Box 21, Folder 16)
  Coordinator's report; correspondence; handwritten paper
- ER+D – Guilderland, 1987-1989 (Box 21, Folder 17)
- ER+D – Duanesburg, 1990 (Box 21, Folder 18)
  Correspondence; outline of training session for August 5-12, 1990, "Initial Expectations for Local Site Coordinators"
- ER+D – Mohawk, 1988 (Box 21, Folder 19)
  Coordinator's report; handwritten paper; implementation action plan
- ER+D – Mount Markham, 1987-1990 (Box 21, Folder 20)
  Presenter's manual for cooperative small groups workshop; coordinator's report; site report; district-wide master plan; handwritten paper
- ER+D – New Hartford, 1987-1992 (Box 21, Folder 21)
  Coordinator's report; site report; correspondence; minutes of regional coordinators meeting
- ER+D – Newburgh, 1992 (Box 21, Folder 22)